Emergency Rescue Committee; Records ger032
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Emergency Rescue Committee Records
1936-1956
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Emergency Rescue Committee
ger032
3 cubic ft.
This collection contains files (photocopies) of the Emergency Rescue Committee, founded in June 1940 in New York by German and American intellectuals and academics soon after the Nazi invasion of France. The files contain letters, registration cards, and other materials of an organization based in New York City concerning some 170 Émigrés and their efforts to flee to the United States from Nazi persecution. Includes files about Alfred Döblin, Hans Natonek, Nelly Sachs, Fritz von Unruh, and Friderike Zweig.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains files (photocopies) of the Emergency Rescue Committee inclduing letters, registration cards, and other materials of an organization based in New York City concerning some 170 Émigrés and their efforts to flee to the United States from Nazi persecution. Includes files about Alfred Döblin, Hans Natonek, Nelly Sachs, Fritz von Unruh, and Friderike Zweig.
Biographical / Historical
The Emergency Rescue Committee (ERC) was founded in June 1940 in New York by German and American intellectuals and academics soon after the Nazi invasion of France. The ERC assisted artists, intellectuals and political dissidents who were under threat in occupied France by providing them financial aid and visas, both legal and illegal, allowing passage to the United States. as an agent of the newly formed Emergency Rescue Committee, Varian Fry raised money and went to France to assist intellectuals that were under the threat of arrest by the Gestapo. By 1950 the Emergency Rescue Committee and International Relief Association combined to form the International Rescue Committee.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Dr. John Spalek in 1979.
Arrangement
The collection has no series, arranged alphabetically
Art; Ethnic Groups; Military and Armed Conflict; Political Science
- Abramovitch, Marc, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Adler Alfred, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Aufhäuser, Siegfried, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bekessy, Emery, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Berczeller, Richard, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Biel, Egon Vitalis (also: Paul Elbogen), 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chneour, Salmon, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Döblin, Alfred (also: Alma Mahler-Werfel; Max Reinhardt; William Dieterle; Bruno Frank; Erika Mann), 1940-1941; 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Dohrn, Klaus (also: Alma Mahler-Werfel), 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Grünwald, Hanna Eisfelder, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Farkas, Aladar, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Fechenbach, Irma, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Feibel, Lotte (Charlotte), 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Feuchtwanger, Lion, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Fischer, Alice, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Fischmann, Lena, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Flake, Minna, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Frank, Elena (also: Leonhard Frank; Thomas Mann), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Frank, Leonhard, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Freud, Ernestine, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Habe, Hans, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Hahn, Hans, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Heiden, Konrad, 1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Heilbut, Iwan (also: Bruno Frank), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Helion, Jean, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Jahiel, Richard, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Jahoda, Marie, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Juhn, Adolf Erich, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Jurkat, Dora, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Jurkat, Ernest, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Kaiser, Eleanore and Hanna, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Kakies, Hans, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Kaufmann, Fritz and Helen, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Keller, Robert (also: Paul Hertz; Kurt R. Grossmann), 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Kessel, Joseph, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Kesten, Hermann, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Kesten, Ida (also: Hermann Kesten), 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Koerner, Herbert, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Koffler, Camilla, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Konopka, Ehrhardt, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Krebs, Jan, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Kriszhaber, Harry, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Kunewalder, Adolf, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Landau, Edmond, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Landshoff, Beate, 40p., 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Landshoff, Eva, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Langendorf, Ernst (also: Rudolf Katz), 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Laumann, Kurt (also: Paul Hertz; Arkadij Gurland), 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Lazarsfeld, Sofie, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Liebling, Otto, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Loewenstein, Sylva, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Malacki, Jean, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Markiewicz, Helmut (also: Paul Pisk), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Masson, Andre, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Mayer, Erna, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Meckauer, Walter (also: Odo von Württemburg; Albert Einstein; Raoul Auernheimer), 1940-1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Mehring, Walter (also: Kurt R. Grossmann; Lyonel Feininger), 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Meyerhof, Walter, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Michaelis, Henri and Cassie (also: Emil Oprecht), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Michel, Peter, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous. Includes form letters, lists, etc., 1941; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Natonek, Hans, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Neumann, Alfred, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Noth, Ernst Erich (also: Jules Romains; Jacques Maritain), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Oesterreicher, John M, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Oettli, Ola, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Oppenheimer-Ophuls, Max (also: Heinrich Schnitzler; Hermann Kesten), 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Osborn, Max (also: Gottfried Bermann-Fischer), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Otzep, Theodore, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Paetel, Karl Otto, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Pauli, Hertha (also: Albert Einstein; Eric Severeid), 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Peiper, Gisela, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Pekelis, Alexander, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Perez-Perez, Emanuel, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Perls, Hugo, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Perls, Kaete, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Pfempfert, Franz, 1940-1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Sachs, Nelly (also: Ricarda Huch), 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Sahl, Hans, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Solzbacher, Wilhelm (also: Hermann Broch; William Sollmann), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Sonnemann, Ulrich (also: Paul Tillich; Thomas Mann), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Spett, Max, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Speyer, Wilhelm (also: Hans Sahl), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Spindel, Pesea Lea, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Spiro, Eugen (also: Hans Staudinger; Erika Mann), 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Stand, Sigmund, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Staub, Herbert Alfred, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Stedeli, Eva (also: Alfred Landé), 1940-1945 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Stein, Alfred, 1941-1952 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Steiner, Willy, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Stern, August and Liesl (also: Norbert Muhlen; Konrad Heiden), 1941 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Stern, Hans, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Sternberg, Ilse, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Steuer, Gertrud, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Strauss, Alfred and Regina, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Strauss, Kurt, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Supervia, Rafel, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Sussmann, Arthur, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Szendrei, Alfred, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Szuecs, Josef, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Tannenwald, Simon, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Tarchiani, Alberto, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Taurer, Bernhard, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Thalbeimer, Siegfried, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Than, Joseph, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Thanhauser, Justin, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Thon, Nathan, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Thormann, Werner, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Tiger, Emil, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Timmermann, Frieda, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Tischler, Victor (also: Robert Thoeren), 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Toepfer, Ludwig and Clema, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Torberg, Friedrich (also: Willi Schlamm), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Tseretelli, Irakli (also: Joseph Buttinger), 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Tuscherer, Erna (also: Kurt Bernhardt), 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Twerska, Karola, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Ullmann, Ludwig (also: Max Reinhardt; Friderike Zweig; Ernst Lothar), 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Vago, Joseph, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Vajna, Ladislas, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Van der Flugt, E, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Varo, Remedios (also: Benjamin Peret), 1941 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Veres, Michel, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Verzeano, Maurice, 1941-1944 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Victor, Paul-Heinz (also: Walther Victor), 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Victor, Walther, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Volski, Sophia, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- von Franckenstein, Joseph, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- von Hildebrand, Dietrich (also: Alvin Johnson), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- von Unruh, Fritz (also: Thomas Mann), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Vordtriede, Kaethe (also: Werner Vordtriede), 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Wachsmann, Konrad (also: Richard Krautheimer; Walter Gropius; Albert Einstein), 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Wang, Erich, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Wagner, Helmut, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Wantoch, Hugo, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Wassermann, Eva (also: Hermann Broch), 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Weigl, Nathan, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Weil, Greta (also: Adrienne Thomas; Hermann Kesten), 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Weinreich, Otto, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Weinstein, Grete, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Weiss, Albin, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Weiss, Mrs. Bernard (also: Albert Grzesinski), 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Weissmann, Alfred, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Weissmann, Josef, 1945-1948 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Welter, Marianna, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Werber, Edwin, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Werner, Harry, 1946-1951 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Wertheim, Margarete, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Wilhartitz, Fritz, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Winkler, Ernst, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Winter, Elizabeth, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Wittlin, Josef (also: Hermann Kesten; Helena Rubenstein), 1940-1951 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Wolf, Alfred (also: Erika Mann; Victoria Wolff), 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Wolf, Willy (also: Ernst Lubitsch), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Wolff, Konrad (also: Reinhold Niebuhr), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Wolff, Kurt, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Wolff, Sigmund, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Wolff-Richter, Ellen, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Wollheim, Gert (also: Leonhard Frank), 1941-1947 (Box 3, Folder 58)
- Wolloch, Leo, 1940-1947 (Box 3, Folder 59)
- Wolski, Berko, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 60)
- Wretzl, Peter, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 61)
- Wronkow, George (also: Manfred George), 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 62)
- Zacharias, Werner, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 63)
- Zaitzeff, Leon, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 64)
- Zappler, Marcell, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 65)
- Zarnower, Teresa, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 66)
- Zeitlin, Boris, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 67)
- Zeitlin, Michael, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 68)
- Zeitlin, Simon, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 69)
- Zernatto, Guido, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 70)
- Zinner, Alfons, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 71)
- Zweig, Friderike (also: Benjamin W.Huebsch; Stefan Zweig), 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 72)